<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Healing motion from abroad to the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12399525</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12399525</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61235</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43195)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 941:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Healing motion from abroad to the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61235:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61235:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A HEALING MOTION From abroad to the PARLIAMENT OF THE Common-wealth OF ENGLAND, SCOTLAND, AND IRELAND, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Dominj 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_publisher">
            <pb facs="tcp:61235:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61235:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Letter ſent to the Publiſher of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing deſcourſe</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur noted affection to ſerve the publick and to do all good offices to ſtrangers, give me this freedome in an unknown habit to apply my ſelfe unto you, to preſent you with the ſenſe of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainers,
<pb facs="tcp:61235:3"/>well-willers to <hi>England,</hi> who look hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully upon the preſent Parliament.</p>
            <p>You need not know who has ſent it; it is not at all materiall, nor uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be known: Believe it as a great truth, that the thing expreſſed here is the hearty deſire of true Proteſtants abroad: and as ſuch let it be made publick.</p>
            <p>You may own this way
<pb facs="tcp:61235:3"/>of receiving it; but are intreated earneſtly to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie no mans curioſity in telling any of your owne conjectures whence it is ſent, it is enough that it comes from abroad, and that no living ſoule of the Engliſh Nation, either in or out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> was ever acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the writing or ſending of it to you. And let this ſuffice to free it from ſuſpition of a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſititious
<pb facs="tcp:61235:4"/>work: behold the Lord is a witneſſe that I ſpeak the Truth. This Motion is wholly from abroad; from none in <hi>England,</hi> and was never thought on by any there. As for matter of partiality, it will free it ſelf to all that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous; others ought not to be regarded: And if you think good you <gap reason="missing" extent="2+ pages">
                  <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61235:4"/>
            <head>A Healing Motion.</head>
            <head type="sub">From abroad to the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THere be Two Paſſions in the corrupt nature of man, which are moſt deſtructive to all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societies: the one is from the Spirit of Envy, or evill deſigning; the other is from the Spirit of Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, or evill ſurmiſing: The laſt can ſee nothing but evill in others, the firſt begets a hatred againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for the good that is ſeen in them. They proceed both from the light of ſelf-love and pride, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets in thoſe that are led by them,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61235:5"/>all manner of diſtance, diviſion and contradiction as to matters of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and all confuſion, ſtrife and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition as to matters of action: whereupon the ruine of all States muſt needs follow; when in the Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof theſe paſſions become ſo predominant, that men are not able to entertain any Chriſtian or civill inclinations to mutual confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and charity, without which no common Intereſt can be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. And although no humane paſſions in natural men are ſo incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as theſe, becauſe they are moſt deeply rooted in the corruption of nature; yet in two ſorts of men, they may be rectified and ſubdued: namely in ſuch who are not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther void of the life of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity in reſpect of God; and in ſuch who making uſe of their Reaſon pretend to ingenuity and common honeſty in reference to men: We ſay in ſuch men, who are upright in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61235:5"/>heart towards God, in the kingdom of his Son, and towards mankind in the State wherein they live, theſe Paſſions will not be prevalent, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the bonds of ſpiritual and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural duties, which Chriſtians and Country-men owe to each other.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe it is conceived that at this time, nothing can diſturbe in humane appearance the welfare of <hi>England</hi> if theſe diſtempers ariſe not, between the Members of this Parliament and the Governours of the State; therefore it is come into the heart of ſome who live abroad, perſons disingaged from all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular relations to any party formed in the Nations, but well willers to the whole Body thereof; to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent without prejudice in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an way of love and ſolliciteouſneſſe, that which they conceive may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent or cure in men of ingenuity, and of a publick ſpirit the forenam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diſtempers, if any (which we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61235:6"/>hope not) ſhould, by weaknes or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, be ſet a working: leſt unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily at ſuch a juncture, the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is natural to all men, turn any of their generous hearts from the aim; and their feet from the way of their chief duty, which is to be helpfull to the State, and faithfully uſefull one to an other in their ſtation, that they may with heart and hand concur together, <hi>to advance the glory of God in their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and the welfare of the Nation which hath put its Intereſts into their hands:</hi> For theſe are the two main ends of their calling unto the high imployment, whereunto by God and man they are admitted; becauſe in the laſt of theſe the private ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and happineſſe of every one is wraped up; and unto the firſt all other Intereſts are ſubordinate. And although Forraigners can take no cogniſance of the choice of perſons to the places whereunto they are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61235:6"/>called, yet becauſe they are not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle concerned in their performing or not performing of the duties, by which the forenamed ends of their calling are attainable, chiefly at this ſeaſonable time when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth is acting abroad, and deliberating at home: Therefore they may lawfully and without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence endeavour to ſuggeſt what they know to be conducible for the attainment of the main Aims fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned; becauſe ſuch as have a common concernment and may be looſers or gainers together, ought to minde each other of the means and wayes by which their Intereſt may be advanced. Now it is out of all doubt that much of the temporall wellfare of all Forraign Proteſtants is involved in the good ſettlement, well-being and proſperity of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to carry on the common cauſe, which by a ſpeciall providence at this time it hath embraced, to make
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61235:7"/>amends for the former failing in this kind, over which all Proteſtants had cauſe to complain and the honeſt godly ſouls at home lamented.</p>
               <p>It ſhall then be ſuppoſed in this Diſcourſe not only that the Choice is lawfull, but alſo that the perſons choſen are qualified with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments requiſite for their places, that is, with a true ſenſe of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and with the right uſe of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reaſon in humane affaires. To ſuch then this plain motion is made by thoſe who abroad wiſh well to <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That ſeeing their hand is now at the plough, they would not look backward but forward:</hi> That is, That they would ſettle their hearts to ſettle the State, in a way of carrying on the common Intereſt of Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple both within and without the Nation; and that they would not intangle themſelves in the diſputes of times paſt, and things paſt reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61235:7"/>which can produce nothing but diſcontent and diſtraction between themſelves at home, with diſcredit and diſadvantage to the Nation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. And to open this matter a little further; even to the meaneſt of all mens capacities, though never ſo much prepoſſeſſed with the thoughts of partiality, we ſhall ſay that the main Intereſt of all Gods people every where is twofold. Firſt That in their dayes they may ſee the manifeſtation of Gods glory, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced amongſt themſelves to be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to their poſterity. Secondly, That their own temporal well being may be ſettled in a durable courſe, which in humane reaſon will not be ſubject to ſudden alterations. And to carry on thoſe deſignes, as the care and faithfulneſſe of thoſe that are intruſted with a Parliamentary Power ought in the fear of God to be engaged, ſo to help foreward the performance of the work it ſelf
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61235:8"/>in our dayes; let it be free for For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners to repreſent their thoughts concerning the means, without which theſe deſigns cannot poſſibly and by which they may infallibly be carried on to ſome perfection. And to this end, the nature of the main thing aymed at, namely, the glory of our God being made known, the means by which it may be advanced, and in order thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way to ſettle the Common welfare of the State will evidently appear.</p>
               <p>The glory of God then is chiefly made known and manifeſt in the fruits of his goodneſs to his people, where is to be diſcerned who Gods people are, and what the fruits of his goodneſſe are unto them. The People of God are they that know his name in Chriſt, that own it and will be called by it; that worſhip him in ſpirit and truth, according to his revealed Word and Will by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61235:8"/>Chriſt, and that through Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone make him their refuge.</p>
               <p>The fruits of his goodneſſe to this his people are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That having revealed himſelf unto them, and called them effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to himſelf out of this evill world, they are ſet unchangably under the Banner of his love in the new Covenant, and his Spirit, Word and Ordinances dwell with them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That by this Spirit, Word and Ordinances, they are inabled and directed to ſerve him all the dayes of their life in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe, being freed from the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and fear of all their enemies.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And that they have a ſure hope to poſſeſſe a Kingdome that can not be ſhaken, when the things that are ſhaken ſhall be removed. As in the enjoyment of theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings Gods people is made happy; ſo in the appearance thereof upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61235:9"/>them his glory is made manifeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world: He then that will in his place advance the manifeſtation of this glory, ought to further ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his abilitie Gods people to ſtand under the enjoyment of theſe bleſſings.</p>
               <p>Now if it be asked by what means and how can the manifeſtation of this Glory be advanced by Men? To this it may be Anſwered, That no man can advance it otherwiſe then by ſetting himſelf to become a receptacle thereof; and by convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his place the evidence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of unto others. From whence it will follow, that if the Members of this Parliament, are men who have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſet themſelves to be recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of theſe fruits of Gods goodnes: if they know the true advantage &amp; how to make right uſe of their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for God; and if they really will lay to heart how they ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the manifeſtation of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61235:9"/>to their own Nation, and the men of this Generation; then we may infer that this Deſign will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly proſper in their hand, and be carried on by them in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtation: but if any void of theſe thoughts, be enclined to envy and jealouſie againſt his neighbours for private occaſions, or againſt thoſe who have managed the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique affairs of State, if he thinks of quarrelling with them, and how to ravell into their matters odiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, making uſe of his place to carry on ſome deſigne againſt them: let him look to his own heart in the fear of God, let him judge that a heart in that frame is no receptacle of the goodneſſe of God; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently is not upright towards the main aym of a Parliamentary Station and calling: whence will follow, that he who is poſſeſſed therewith and led therewith, can never approve himſelf in the Truſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61235:10"/>committed unto him, either honeſt towards God and his people, or faithfull to the State.</p>
               <p>Now if ſuch a one (being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to himſelfe that he is judged by theſe words, which diſcover the error of his way) ſhall deſire to make ſtreighter paths for his feet, leaſt that which is lame in his poore and narrow ſoul be turned out of the way; let him not ſlight the plain ſuggeſtions which here are to be made, but ſeriouſly with a ſingle Chriſtian eye reflect <hi>Firſt upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, Secondly upon the people of God,</hi> and <hi>Thirdly upon the preſent ſtate of the Common-wealth of</hi> England.</p>
               <p>Reflecting upon himſelfe let him be jealous over his own ſoul; and ſeek to diſcerne the frame of that Spirit by which he was ledd, that he may know with what Chriſtian In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations towards God and men he ſtands in his place; for if he cannot judge himſelf how ſhall he be able
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61235:10"/>(as a parliament member ought) to judge and rectifie others? If he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take the beam out of his owne eye, how ſhall he take the mote out of his Neighbours? If then he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to go out of himſelfe, and to lay himſelfe aſide, that he may be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to ſerve others through love, if he ſhall be deſirous to receive all to the glory of God as Chriſt hath received us; and in like manner to be received by all: If in this way of receiving and being received, he hath gotten his minde compoſed to mannage the publique concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſtianity without mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring and diſputing, without wrathfull mallice and ſtrife; being enabled in meekneſſe to receive and to hold forth to all the light which he hath received: If he hath been taught in bearing with diſſenters to diſcerne their principles, to make a difference between thoſe that keep the foundation and thoſe that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61235:11"/>it; to deal patiently with all that they may recover themſelves out of the ſnares of the devill: and if he hath ſtudied the wayes of Peace, of Truth, of Righteouſneſſe, to be found not only blameleſſe and harmleſſe towards all men, as he would have all men to be found to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards himſelfe; but alſo to hold forth the word of life, and to ſhine as a light in that life before men. If (we ſay reflecting upon himſelfe) he diſcern without flattery, in his own ſpirit, this frame wrought by grace, or a ſincere deſire and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of endeavours to have it wrought: he may entertain hopes to become through mercy ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and uſefull in his place for the advancement of Gods glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his people. But if to theſe thoughts and deſires his ſpirit is an utter ſtranger, if with theſe motions and endeavours, he hath not at all been hitherto acquainted; let him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61235:11"/>judge himſelf in the preſence of the Lord before he be judged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: let him not play the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite to meddle with holy things, and take the name of our God in vain, whiles his heart is far from him: For the <hi>Lord will not hold him guilty who taketh his name in vaine.</hi> Let him not preſume above his line, nor meddle with that whereunto he is not called nor ſet apart: for no man can be a Veſſell of Honour in the hand of the Lord, for the houſe of his glory to ſerve therein, whom he hath not endowed with theſe Principles and inclinations, by which the way of true Chriſtianity is held forth amongſt the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his children to the reſt of the world.</p>
               <p>Reflecting therefore in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place upon the People of God, he ought to diſcern the duty which by his place with his beſt abilities he oweth unto them: namely, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61235:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>he is appointed to bear them as they are the veſſels of the Lord; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven all the veſſels of great and ſmal quantitie, <hi>from the Veſſels of cups, to all the veſſels of flagons.</hi> The cups are the younger ſort, the flagons the elder: The Schools for the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the Churches for the elder are to be borne up; and the breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of many generations therein to be repared; and that is to be done by ſo much Publique Authority as God hath given to <hi>nurſing Fathers,</hi> and with ſo much care and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as becometh Elders and Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in a way ſutable to the Goſpel, and to <hi>the day of Chriſts power.</hi> He that cares not for theſe Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Gods people, to advance in his ſtation the evidencing of Gods goodneſſe, unto the ſeed plots of the Nation, as well as to the plants of full growth, but would have all ingroſſed to ſome one party with the excluſion of others; cannot be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61235:12"/>ſaid <hi>to ſerve the generation of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and conſequently is not found faithfull to the publique truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him; for if he will be counted a Shepherd or leader of the flock, he ought according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and in the capacity of his place, <hi>to carry the Lambs in his boſom, and lead tenderly thoſe that are with young;</hi> to overſee the husbandry of mens ſouls, and <hi>to ſeek the peace and proſperity of Jeruſalem;</hi> that <hi>the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of holineſs</hi> by the goodneſſe of the Lord, may reſt manifeſtly upon his people, that <hi>all wicked doers may be cut off from the Citty of the Lord,</hi> in that way which the Lord himſelfe hath appointed, and taught the Judges of his people as at the firſt, and the Councellors as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. For the way of the Lord is plain as well in the ſtreets of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon, as in the path of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and they that will ſee may ſee the means to be made uſe of; and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61235:13"/>find a Directory for the application of the ſame without difficulty.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they will ſee that the word revealed in the Law and Teſtimony, ought not to be concealed from Gods people: That the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ought to be countenanced and upheld: that the faithfull Teachers ought not to be <hi>removed into a corner</hi> and thruſt away from the faithfull of the Land, either by ſubtilty or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence: That the Office of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry ſhould not be made contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible, and become an object of ſtrife and contradiction. That fit men endowed with Ruling and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall abilities, ſhould be ſet a part to dwell before the Lord, and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the charge of his houſe without diſtraction, they ſhould be <hi>counted worthy of double honour,</hi> they ſhould not want ſufficient food nor durable cloathing, nor the reſpect due unto their faithfullneſſe in their places.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they will ſee further
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61235:13"/>that the liberty of the Saints ſhould alſo be maintained: That none ſhould be ſuffered to aſſert or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt <hi>to have dominion over the faith of Gods children;</hi> nor <hi>to put a yoak or ſnare upon their conſciences:</hi> yet that this liberty ſhould not be ſuffered on the other hand to run out into li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe by the diſſolution of all rule; or the neglect of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly wayes of mutuall edification, under a pretence, that Chriſt is the ſole Lord and Ruler in and over the conſcience, and that in the <hi>latter dayes all ſhall be taught of God,</hi> for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Chriſt doth by his power rule the whole world, yet he rules his Saints within his Church, and hath never exempted their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from the rules of his word and Spirit, nor promiſed to teach any without theſe as held forth in his Church; nor purchaſed a priviledge to any, not to ſtand under the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his revealed will in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61235:14"/>Law and Teſtimony given to his Church; nor limited the power of his vicegerents over the ſociety of men ſo, that it ſhould be unlawfull for them to ſee the rules obſerved, which he hath given to mankind, and to the aſſemblies of his Saints (which they are commanded to protect) whereby the glory of his goodneſſe unto them is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they will ſee alſo that not onely in civill Adminiſtrations, but in the Aſſemblies of the Saints God hath appointed diſtinct cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: That theſe are regulated by him, becauſe he is <hi>the God of peace and good order,</hi> and not of diſorder and confuſion: That the limits of theſe callings ſhould be diſcerned and obſerved, and that men who in humane affaires have no rule over their own ſpirit, and yet take upon them to rule all Spiritual matters, onely by the unruly motions of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61235:14"/>their private fancies; ſhould not be hearkened unto, but be brought to know their bounds in ſpeaking and acting, and conſequently that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould be made obedient to the Apoſtles Law, which is, <hi>that they ſhould keep ſilence in the Church,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is a ſhame for them to ſpeak in the congregation,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34, 35. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12</note> or to take upon them <hi>to teach and to uſurp Authority over men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, they will furthermore ſee, that the Saints ought to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and walk in love; to owne one another in that <hi>whereunto they are come,</hi> to agree in the clear rules of mutual edification and removing offences, which diſhonour the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: To <hi>bear one anothers burdens,</hi> and to make manifeſt their agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and brotherly union in the way of Truth and Peace, till God bringing them unto a compleat growth in Chriſt, and their <hi>modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being made known to all men,</hi> they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61235:15"/>may <hi>attain unto the meaſure of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the fullneſſe of Chriſt, and be no more carried up and downe as Children with every wind of doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the uſe of theſe means and the diſcreet ſetting of them a foot, the reproach which hath been caſt upon <hi>England</hi> by their adverſaries with much induſtry and artifice, ſhall be taken off from the face of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, in the courſe of their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible obſerving of Ordinances; and the obloquie of the ignorant, which by this occaſion hath been raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the Reformed Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad ſhall be ſilenced, and then the communion of Saints with Forrain Churches may be ſet a foot and hopefully continued till the prayer of Chriſt be fullfilled;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.10, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> wherein he deſired that all <hi>who ſhall beleeve in his name by the word of his Apoſtles, may be one as the Father is in him, and he is in the Father, that they alſo may be one in them, to the end that the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61235:15"/>world may beleeve,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16</note> 
                  <hi>that the Father hath ſent his only begotten Son into the world, that whoſoever believeth in him, may not periſh, but have life everlaſting.</hi> For this is the great teſtimony of the love of God and of his goodneſſe towards his people; and this is that which is to be made manifeſt unto the world, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in his place of truſt in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or elſe where, hath no ſincere aim to glorify God in the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this truth, whereunto all the forenamed duties by the Spirit and Word are made ſubordinate, in hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it forth unto the world by his people; he cannot approve his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to be upright towards God for the concernments of his Saints and the truth of Chriſtianity, not faithfull to the Commonwealth whereof he is a member, becauſe it is knowne that no Commonwealth of this world ſhall henceforth ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt long or finally proſper, but in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61235:16"/>order to the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt; as grounded upon this, and upheld by this way of ſettlement, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.11, 12.</p>
               <p>Therefore in the third place, if he will reflect upon the preſent ſtate of the Commonwealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and doth know that Chriſt by his kingdome doth uphold <hi>the pillars of the Earth, till he ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit all Nations;</hi> and that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths of the world have a being only till his Elect be gathered out of them: and that in <hi>ſeeking the kingdome of God firſt and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> to be ſettled in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, all other welfare will be added unto it: If theſe Maximes are known and preſuppoſed, then the temporal concernments of a State may and ought to be laid to heart in the next place; and therein the duty of a faithfull Patriot and good Commonwealths man ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidered: whereby every
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61235:16"/>one who is not void of all reaſon and honeſty, will be taught in ſuch a juncture of time, to lay aſide in his publick place, all private inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and grudges, and look to the preſent common concernment wherewith the Parliament is intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in reſpect of men: Which we conceive is briefly this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To preſerve the ſafety and to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the peace of the Nation at home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To procure the proſperity, and to maintain the Credit thereof abroad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore his faithfulneſs will be to imploy his abilities, induſtry, and authority, to make uſe of the means and wayes, which God and Nature hath fitted, and put in his hand, to further theſe purpoſes; of which means our thoughts, we hope may be offered here; and as they are without partiality; ſo they will be received without prejudice, by all that are intelligent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>To preſerve then the ſafety, it is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61235:17"/>abſolutely neceſſary, that ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent and allowed form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be ſettled therein: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the experience of all ages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to ſound reaſon doth ſhew that nothing doth ruine a people ſo ſuddenly, and ſo abſolutly as Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, which is a ſtate wherein no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being viſible, it is free for every one to do by himſelfe in private, and towards others in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, whatſoever his own fantaſie or his unruly paſſion doth ſuggeſt unto him: which needs muſt fall out when there is no common Rule to walk by, nor any due reſpect had to any ſuperiour. Now how farre the Government ſettled in a great multitude of men (whoſe humours and capacities, being by nature, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, and cuſtome, many wayes different, and in ſome things op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite; yet have all alike an equall hand in the Government of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) doth naturally tend to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61235:17"/>unſettlement of all rule in a Commonwealth, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to an unlimited permiſſion, for every leader of a party to get power and thereby to oppoſe and diſturbe the way of ſuch as diſſent from him, or for every member of a party to do for himſelf what ever ſeemeth good in his own eyes (we ſay) how far a Government ſo conſtituted in the hands of ſuch a multitude, doth naturally tend to a perpetuall unſettlement of all bonds of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, ſpirituall, civill and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſocieties, we ſhall not ſet our ſelves to lay open; it may be ſeen daily abroad in all meerly popular Governments, nor will it be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, nor is it expedient in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe for proof hereof, to make any obſervation upon the changes lately fallen out in <hi>England,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſuch a way of Government; but it will ſuffice to take notice, that no Forreigners ever could perceive
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61235:18"/>any ground of ſafety or ſettlement in that Commonwealth, till it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the Aſſembly which in the year 1653 was called, and acted as a Parliament, perceiving its own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency (by reaſon of its diviſions within it ſelf) to ſettle matters in a right frame; did reſigne the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Governing into the hands of a few, over whom a Head was ſet which hath ſince given ſufficient proof to the world, both of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to his Nation, and of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities to Govern, with Diligence, Courage, Foreſight, &amp; Moderation; and it is believed abroad, that as long as he ſhall continue in the fear of God, and not be lifted up in his heart, his courſe will not be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted; and as long as this courſe which by him and his Counſell is taken ſhall continue without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, that the State will be more and more ſettled in a flouriſhing condition, and not only remain ſafe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61235:18"/>within it ſelf, but become daily more and more formidable to all that are enemies unto it.</p>
               <p>Upon which conſideration, as all Forraigners, who wiſh well to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (for the Intereſt which in the Common Cauſe of Proteſtants, by this Mans conduct it hath begun to embrace) do ſtand amazed at the wonderfull hand of God in raiſing him, beyond all mens thoughts, and in keeping him againſt ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate plots: ſo they hope that the <hi>faithfull in the land,</hi> and the Patriots of the Commonwealth in their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Aſſembly, will no leſſe be ſenſible than Forraigners are of this ſtrange Providence; and in this their Meeting ſet their hearts to concur with it and carry it on: not only by a confirmation of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (with the limitations alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy agreed upon) but by an additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that reſpect thereunto, which will make it more conſiderable, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61235:19"/>unqueſtionably receivable, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Fundamental Statute laws of the Nation) by all as well at home as abroad. For by ſuch a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the Government, the ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the State will be in all humane appearance henceforth ſecured from all dangerous commotions and conſpiracies, which otherwiſe will never be wanting ſo long as the Pretenders to an abſolute govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have power or can conſpire with the enemies of the State, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe the quiet thereof, and repoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe themſelves of their pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Thus then the ſafety of the Nation may be ſecured at this time from many dangerous plots; namely, by this addition of Authority to the Government; and conſequently by this means, the Peace thereof at home, will alſo be continued and confirmed; becauſe the quietneſſe of a State depends upon the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ruling Power, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61235:19"/>reſt long ſetled in the hands of a Multitude, chiefly when there is a neceſſity of managing a War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, whereunto the united ſtrength and Counſel of a Nation muſt concur, to make it ſucceſſefull: And how far the government of ſtrength and Counſel can be mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by a multitude ſucceſſefully to continue, is not eaſily conceivable in notion, far leſſe approved by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. <hi>Solomon</hi> hath indeed ſaid, <hi>That in the multitude of Counſellours is ſafety,</hi> becauſe a multitude can ſuggeſt all manner of difficulties and dangers to be avoided, and expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents to be followed, whereof the choice may be made by a few: but we believe not that ever any wiſe man ſaid, that the power of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in a multitude was ſafe, or could be well ſettled: Therefore a multitude may be heard in the way of conſultation, but the reſult of the deliberation, and the Power to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61235:20"/>the execution muſt be intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a few, chiefly when the State is in a war abroad, and the peace thereof at home is doubtfull.</p>
               <p>But concerning the continuance of peace and quietneſſe within doors, the chief meanes thereof is not ſo much the ſettlement of the Governing power in a few, as the unity of thoſe who mannage the publick counſels in their aimes of adminiſtring Juſtice to all without partiality, and of permitting a due liberty to all who refuſe not to be Governed by lawes, and are not tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent nor under the blame of any accuſation, for Juſtice is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and liberty well ordered, is like unto the Channell wherein Peace, and quietneſſe followes in the hearts and aſſemblies of men: the counſells then which we enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine without partiality, to ſettle Juſtice with freedome to all, being unanimuſly perſecuted by the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61235:20"/>of Peace in a Nation. Now the great Councell of a great Nation convocated for extroardinary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions cannot be conſtituted of a few; and although in an Aſſembly of many Counſellors, when men come together as men, that is to ſpeak their own ſenſe, there muſt needs be a great variety of opinions eſpecially in circumſtantial matters, concerning the manner how to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on a buſineſſe; yet if their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be honeſt towards one and the ſame aime, they will find a way jointly to concur to ſome concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the main, leaving the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial manner of doing that which ſhall be judged fit to be done, unto the prudence of thoſe who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the adminiſtration of the Government.</p>
               <p>And although all diviſion of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties into parties, whereby ſome men joyn to drive on ſome ſpecial deſigne as diſtinct from others, doth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61235:21"/>proceed originally from ſelfwil and ſome predominant luſt; yet parties are not formed in great or ſmall Aſſemblies, otherwiſe then by the breaking forth of ſtrife and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, when in conſultations about common concernments diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opinions are held forth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns formed; or when in the ſame deſign different wayes are ſet a foot to proceed therein. This rock then is to be avoided, for the Unity is commonly ſplit thereupon: and to avoid it we conceive, there are but two wayes; the one relates to the Perſons who are imployed to give Counſell, the other relates to the Manner of conſulting which may be ſet a foot. As to the Perſons, they ought freely and conſcionably pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and ſet their hearts to abjure all purpoſes and thoughts of fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or following a party, for any particular deſigne, by cleaving only to the common aime of publique
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61235:21"/>ſafety, Peace, Proſperity and Credit of the Nation; for ſo far as any doth begin to break to the particular ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of this or that party; ſo much he deviates from the true aim of his calling to his publique im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment: therefore in order to this reſolution he ought in manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publique Counſels to avoid carefully all paſſionate diſputes, perſonal touches and contradictory debates: and propoſing his own advice with the reaſons thereof in a ſerious, grave, ſingle hearted way, as diſcharging his conſcience in his place, leave the judgment thereof unto others: but becauſe all men chiefly thoſe that are quick and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, have not ſuch a reſtraint upon their own ſpirits, when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the weaknes of others, as not to run out upon by matters, and play upon them, which is to trifle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> waighty matters; therefore this in conveniency which breeds di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61235:22"/>with open or ſecret diſcontents can hardly be avoided when Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are mannaged by extemporary diſcourſes: Another courſe then may be ſet a foot in the way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation, by which perſonall refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions will be avoided, and the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of diſcontentment prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which we conceive is this. That the manner of propoſing advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould not be extemporary but premeditate, wherein the matter to be adviſed on being foreknowen; every one ſhould be obliged to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his ſenſ poſitively in brief writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Aphoriſms or Articles concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the means which he doth judge moſt fit to be followed or avoided in proſecuting the thing aimed at in the deliberation. And although in this way different means will be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered nevertheleſs all advices being poſitive &amp; directed more or leſſe to one main end; they will for the moſt part be found either coordinate or
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61235:22"/>ſubordinate one to another; then the means on all hands offered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid together by way of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, ſuch as in ſubſtance agree moſt, and have leaſt difficulty, may be taken up and made uſe of by thoſe who are intruſted with the execution of the worke.</p>
               <p>Thus in the multitude of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells will be ſafety, when all opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are heard, when the partiality of deſignes, the paſſion of debates, and the trifling in propoſals is avoided, and the real advices ſo farr as an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement is found in them, are put together, to make up one determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, nor ought any to be ſo ſelfe conceited of his own judgment, as to diſallow the conſent which will be found in many, although his owne opinion is not followed.</p>
               <p>How farr this way of conſulting may be ſet a foot in a Parliament; we know not, we leave it to the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent conſideration of thoſe who
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61235:23"/>without partiality minde the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good rather then a private de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. But it is knowne that elſwhere in great counſels, this way is practiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; that it is practicable amongſt ingenuous men is out of all doubt.</p>
               <p>There is one difficulty more by which the mindes of men are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times devided and reſolutions ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, it relates to the Publique Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens whereof a Common-wealth ſtands in need, chiefly in times of warre; namely how to raiſe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent contributions to maintain the neceſſary charges thereof. Here the naturall right and freedom of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to diſpoſe of their own ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, comes in competition with the neceſſity of a State: Where then is to be conſidered; how farre every one is bound to ſuſpend, or give up his private right in his poſſeſſions towards the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Publique wel-fare. Now we finde that in moſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61235:23"/>of Europe this freedome is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt; the Subjects being made ſlaves to the will ef their Rulers, not only in warre but in times of peace: But in <hi>England</hi> the people by their Repreſentatives in Parliament taxe themſelves: Their wiſedome and generoſity being made acquainted with the dangers whereinto the Nation is brought by the attempts of Adverſaries, doth induce them, freely to part with ſome, to preſerve all; and rather to give up all to be managed for a lawfull defence, then to looſe all for want of courage and reſolution. In this caſe then a cleer Demonſtration of the Neceſſity ariſing from without, when all Neighbours are in Arms; when no common ordinary charges can ſecure the State, and when the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for publick ſafety can ſuffer no delay, will ſway the Reſolutions of reaſonable men to provide for themſelves and their poſterity: and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61235:24"/>how far at this time the War with <hi>Spain,</hi> and the uncertain friendſhip of other neighbours, may bring ſuch a neceſſity upon the ſtate, we need not to mention; it is no doubt bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowne to thoſe that mannage the publick in <hi>England;</hi> and can be better inſinuated to the members of the Parliament then we are able to ſuggeſt. But herein certainly is the faithfulneſs of a good Patriot ſeen to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his native Country, that he will do his utmoſt endeavours to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite all honeſt hearts in Counſels and affections, and all the ſtrength that may be had at home, when imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent dangers are abroad; not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring private diſcontents to grow up to the diſturbance of the publick at any time: but leaſt of all then, when by their increaſe all may be hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; or the ſucceſſe of neceſſary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings interrupted: which gives us ſome cauſe to wonder at the Motion which is made in a little
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61235:24"/>diſcourſe, called <hi>The Healing Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> propounded &amp; reſolved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſaid to be made by a man of parts: Wherein we perceive a new deſign, as it were made in the ayre, and which in ſubſtance is onely this:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That a party which is ſaid to have ſtood up for an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Liberty both in their civill and religious courſes, being now divided within themſelves, by the emergencies of the way wherein they were; ſhould be united again, and endeavour to meet in a military po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, to frame a new conſtitution of Government unto themſelves, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it upon the Nation; without any other principle or rule of Righteouſnes preſuppoſed or agreed upon amongſt themſelves, for future ſafety and Peace; then their own growing light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which to us ſeems ſo wilde and uncertain a foundation of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of conſultation in State affairs, that it is to be admired any rational man ſhould ever imagine
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61235:25"/>that any ſettlement can be procured thereby, either to a people divided into parties, ſuch as now are in great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> or to any one party divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from it ſelf, whiles each ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſion, according to its growing light wreſtles for the maſtery with the other. For in the whole diſcours there's no common ground of unity offered, nor any rule or character of true light ſuggeſted, whereby their aims ſhould be fixed, or their Counſels and actions directed to a publick good; but the meer notion of a popular liberty which hath no bounds. If it be ſaid that the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and rule of ſelf abaſement and ſelf denial before God is propoſed as the onely means of their agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which God will appear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. We Anſwer, that if this rule be truly followed, men will indeed be kept from preſuming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their line. But firſt, how can any aſſurance be had, that a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61235:25"/>part of three Nations coming all of them voluntarily (that is acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally) together, will truly intend to deny themſelves? Who ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern this frame of ſpirit in them? Who ſhal ſeparate the vile from the precious, if falſe brethren privily come in to betray and divide their thoughts? and if it is not imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that either they all, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of them, will be ſuch as deny themſelves truly; or that thoſe who are truly ſuch can bediſcerned: then they are not like to agree, but a new breach will fall out amongſt them, and all will be again in confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But ſecondly, ſuppoſing this to be poſſible, that men comming together to ſetle a Soveraignty in themſelves, and that in a military poſture (as is ſuppoſed ſhould be done) can whiles they intend this, intend alſo at the ſame time to deny themſelves in the uſe of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty and Power (we ſay) ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61235:26"/>this to be poſſible, which ſeems nevertheleſſe to imply a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of intentions; the queſtion then will be; What can they by way of Counſel ſettle, or put to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution in humane affairs? How ſhall they practiſe their ſelf deniall? ſhall every one who pretends to a grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light, be obliged not to uſe it? or in his ſoverraign capacity not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to bring others under the rule of it? for if he preſumes to do this, how ſhal he be ſaid to deny himſelf? and if he doth it not, where is the ſoveraignty, and how ſhall ever any thing be ſettled in the way of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? Thirdly, Suppoſe a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councel of honeſt well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men come together as is ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, who all walk by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their growing light; and have none other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon rule but the aim of Liberty; can it be ſuppoſed that they will all have the ſame meaſure of light in their underſtanding, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61235:26"/>latitude of liberty in their will? No certainly &amp; if ſo how ſhal they agree? Can it be conceived that every one wil deny his own light or his aim of liberty, to ſubmit it to the will of an other? If ſo, why will they not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſſe in the will of thoſe that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne? If not ſo, what poſſibility will there be of any agreement, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept there be ſome common rule by which they may agree and be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in Counſels? Certainly it is not likely, chiefly if what we hear be true; namely that it is found by experience that the men who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to talke moſt of their light (they are called Quakers) are ſo drunck with their owne imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that leaſt of all men they deny themſelves in any thing. Nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed can they do it if their liberty be only this, to admit of none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rule in humane and divine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, but their owne light neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to follow it, as it doth grow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61235:27"/>them: And what confuſion this will beget to unſettle all Humane Societies, and what diviſion in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations, we need not to mention: nay indeed with ſuch there can be no uſe of any conſultation, where none is free to follow any reaſoning with others, and is bound up only to his owne growing light which he counts infallible; and which all ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall men will count a kinde of frenſie. Therefore from the ſuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and by the principle offered in the <hi>Healing Queſtion,</hi> there cannot poſſibly any Healing be, or ground of ſafety and peace be laid unto a wavering State. And truly the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion as it is there propounded and reſolved, (if we may ſpeak our ſenſe of it) tends only to the unſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all that is now eſtabliſhed, and to caſt downe that which hath been built upon former ruines, by the more ſtayed and ſounder part of the Nation; which hitherto hath
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61235:27"/>with good ſucceſſe preſerved the whole in peace and ſafety, by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the oppoſit parties at home from oppreſſing each other; and Foraigners from invading and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying them all. Therefore we ſhall leave that notion of liberty, ſet forth and clothed with good lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as a deſtructive Notion to all peace and ſafety in the Nations, and fitted only to raiſe the ſpirit of a diſcontented party to move to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſome change or other; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it cannot know either where to reſt or what courſe it would ſhape to come to a ſetlement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Thus having expreſſed our hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wiſhes towards that which we conceive to be the fundamentall well-being of the State and Nation, we ſhall not need to extend our thoughts much further to ſpeak of the Superſtructures of Proſperity and Credit, how they may be built thereupon: For theſe will natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61235:28"/>ſpring up as branches out of a fruitfull tree well rooted and well planted. The State being the Tree, the root thereof is the honeſty of the heart of the Rulers towards God &amp; their Nation, for to advance his glory &amp; their welfare. The body or ſtem thereof, is the frame of Laws to ſettle the Government, in a way of Juſtice to preſerve peace and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy freedome well ordered. The main Branches that grow up from hence are the Proſperity and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of a Nation; and although theſe two branches take their growth commonly together, ſo that the one is ſeldome without the other; yet in the Notions of their nature they are diſtinguiſhed; and the means whereby each of them is maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and procured, are neither imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the ſame, nor ſo nearly link<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together that they cannot be ſeparated; otherwiſe all the wayes and meanes of outward proſperity
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61235:28"/>(ſuppoſe the Spaniſh maſſacring of poore Indians contrary to faith gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) to gain Riches and Power; would be counted honorable: But to ſpeak briefly our ſenſe of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and means of theſe two, we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it thus: That Proſperity in our motion is nothing elſe but the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing condition of a people by the increaſe of Riches and Strength; and that Credit or Reputation is nothing elſe but the honorable eſteem which others have of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in reſpect of their Vertues, namely Piety, Juſtice, Truth, Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe, Conſtancie, Courage, Wiſdome and ſuch like; whence it appears that although it falls out in the world; that a rich and ſtrong people are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly in eſteem with their neighbours; and ſuch as are in good eſteem with all may grow in riches and ſtrength; yet the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and direct wayes and meanes of procuring true Credit and Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61235:29"/>are different from thoſe which procure and uphold Riches and Strength.</p>
               <p>The proper meanes to procure Riches is Induſtry applied to Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry and Trade; under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Husbandry, we comprehend aſwell that Induſtry which is above ground about the fruits of the earth; and all animate living creatures, which move upon it; as that which is under ground, about Minerals and Stones and ſuch like. Under the notion of Trade we underſtand all induſtry uſed to purchaſe, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, to tranſport and to put off commodities by Land or by Sea; to which we refer all manner of Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, which beget all trade; and the Art of Navigation which foments all Trade, and is fomented by the induſtry of Fiſhing. All theſe Advantages <hi>England</hi> has to inrich it ſelf withall; as much if not more then any one nation whatſoever;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61235:29"/>if then Induſtry to improve theſe advantages be not wanting; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be wanting to make the Nation flouriſh in wealth. Now to ſtir up induſtry in people not dull, but by nature lively and active is no difficult matter, if their leaders be awake, and lay to heart the way to ſettle them in a courſe thereof: which may be done by obſerving the advantages, which by reaſon of ſloth, or for want of skill being neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by their own, are laid hold of and improved by others. To this effect ſhould be ſearched into what the variety of native commodities moſt proper to the Nation is; and what there is of common Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, which others have alſo, what ſtore there is of each ſort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how much of each the Nation it ſelf conſumes; how much want thereof is amongſt Foraigner: how both ſorts of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities ſhould be improved by Manufactures; how moſt advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61235:30"/>brought abroad to the utmoſt Market: how the trade ſhould be regulated to be juſt and laſting: how the commodities made moſt merchandable; the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſafe from Pyracy; how the Sea Ports ſhould be made not onely commodious Harbours for Fleets; but Magazins for the tranſportation of foreign commodities from one Nation to another: Such like mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters muſt be thought upon in the way of a State to make a People induſtrious and proſper in wealth: and being wealthy there will be means to put themſelves in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of ſtrength, when ever it is needfull.</p>
               <p>Yet although wealth helps much to further ſtrength, nevertheleſſe ſtrength conſiſts not in it; but it conſiſts chiefly in the wayes of rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing peoples courage to be fit for action; in the uniting of their minds and reſolutions to ſtand for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61235:30"/>cauſe &amp; intereſt; in the training up of youth to hardſhip, and to the experience of action by Sea and by Land; and to the ſubjection unto diſcipline; of all which things we have nothing to ſuggeſt but this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that we conceive it belongeth to the wiſdom and faithfulnes of thoſe who are intruſted to regulate the State of a Nation, to reflect upon theſe things for the benefit thereof; and conſequently to hear the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the moſt experienced men in every kind either within or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Nation, to put it in a way of more induſtry then hitherto hath been obſerved in it: and we wiſh that the envy of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Ephraim</hi> in point of Trade, may not onely ceaſe, but be brought to a Coalition, upon common grounds and rules of profit and pains.</p>
               <p>The laſt thing which we have in our wiſhes is, that the maintaining of the Credit of the Nation may as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61235:31"/>well be underſtood as cared for, by thoſe to whom it is intruſted. It cannot be unknown to any who hath been abroad, at what a low rate the Nation hath been valued at by all Neighbours before this laſt change is befallen to it: wherein it has gotten a Protector to go before it: it becomes us not to ſay what we know of this matter; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly in regard of this it was in no ſmall danger, both at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad undervalued, becauſe Nations ſubſiſt and flouriſh no leſſe by Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Reputation amongſt their Neighbours than by force; for the ſucceſſe of force is uncertain. But God was pleaſed to give beyond all imagination, that ſucceſſe unto the Parliament forces under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of their Generals, which raiſed to a conſiderable degree the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Nations courage, which ſeemed to be loſt. Afterward the exceſſe of their Courage &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61235:31"/>begetting unexpected changes, made the world ſtand in doubt of their wiſedome. But now that which was diſeſteemed is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired. The true Friends (which are none but true Proteſtants) find cauſe to glorifie God and looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his hand with hope in the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: The enemies (which are all Popiſh Agents and baſe Spirited Politicians) are at a ſtand, and in a maze, not knowing where to find their way concerning <hi>England.</hi> If from under ſuch a low eſteem of the wiſedome of the Nation, the credit thereof is thus farre raiſed again by a Protector, what might be done if it had a King of ſuch an Heroick ſpirit, and able con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct? We looke upon the Nation therefore as raiſed from the dead, and ſet upon its feet to act in its true intereſt, from which it was hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore kept back. Formerly the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard had his ſnares upon all the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61235:32"/>Counſells, but theſe are now bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: And we make no doubt but the Wiſe and Generous Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives now aſſembled will maintain the Credit of the Nation againſt him. The ſucceſſe of the warre hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath not been ſuch as could bring gain: Seldome is it ſeen that the beginning of a warre is gainfull, but we conceive it hath not been undertaken ſo much for gain, as for Juſtice and Reputation; and in this reſpect we find it very ſuccesfull; both in reference to the cauſe, and to the event, which may be foreſeen by thoſe that are intelligent: The Proteſtant Cauſe in Europe is ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it; and although in ſuch a vaſt enterpriſe, the event cannot be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly apparent to all; yet it may be perceived, that in a ſhort time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continued, it will certainly ruin the great enemy of the peace of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope; and drain the fountain of his power, and break the Antichriſtian
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61235:32"/>yoak which hitherto for the Papal Intereſt he hath put upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of all Chriſtians, who have dealt with him: We mean the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, by which he is an open enemy to all Chriſtian freedom. A Tyrannie of the higheſt nature that can be imagined; and under which all deſerve to lye; whoſe ſpirit is ſo baſe as not to joyne in oppoſing it; till the upholders of it be made as contemptible, as ever they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be eminent by their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Monarchy: And if there were no more in the quarrel but this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; The Reputation of <hi>England</hi> will be glorious for ever in the mindes of all men of Piety and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; for lifting up a banner againſt it, when the reſt of the world did fit ſtill under it. We ſee daily that ſome Nations make warre with their Neighbours, for raiſing Taxes of money, or infringing the liberty of their Trade; and ſhould not all
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61235:33"/>Chriſtian States become ſenſible of ſuch abominable taxing of the perſons and lives of their Subjects; and of the infringment of the whol liberty of their Goſpell profeſſion? it ſhall therefore henceforth truly be ſaid that no Nation is ſenſible of true liberty but <hi>England;</hi> and that all deſerves to be ſlaves that take not up this quarrell with it. And chiefly thoſe who for the love of filthy lucre, either ſtrengthen the hands of Tyrannie by aſſiſting him in his occaſions of warre; or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their ſtrength and the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance due to thoſe <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  </hi> do oppoſe him. Therefore we are confident that the pious &amp; generous Repreſentatives of the highly eſteemed Nation of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will not be wanting in ſupplies or ſtick at extraordinary charges. Herein then what ever the event of the warre may be, will the Piety, the Juſtice and the Courage of the Nation be renowned to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61235:33"/>poſterity, that they alone have ſtood up, for the freedome of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, not for themſelves alone; but for all that make profeſſion of the truth, and this ſhould raiſe the ſpirits of all honeſt men ſo much the more, by how much it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that Chriſt hath raiſed a man, as it were out of nothing, beyond all mens expectation to take this worke in hand: Whence the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the enterpriſe cannot be doubted of; ſeeing it is the way of God to evidence miraculouſly his power, and to overthrow the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt of the earth by that which hath the leaſt appearance, Bleſſed be his Name for it; and let all that love him in truth ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is one thing more wherein the Reputation of <hi>England</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, which although it is not ſo apparent to the world as the former enterpriſe, yet in it ſelf it is no leſſe conſiderable; and to the intelligent
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61235:34"/>who have notice of it, is a matter of no leſſe rejoycing: We have heard of it, and conceive if it be proſecuted (of which we doubt not) as it is hopefully begun, it will advance the ſpirituall intereſt of Saints in one another, and the kingdome of Chriſt thereby more effectually, then the breaking of the outward tirannical power of the Adverſarie can do. It is the Deſigne of taking away the diviſions which are amongſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and ſetting a Religious cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency a foot amongſt them; for the propagating of the Truth wherein they are agreed. At this Deſigne as the godly on both ſides are comforted and raiſed in Spirit to hope chearfully for a bleſſed enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the knowledge of the Son of God; ſo the Adverſaries of the Truth are more then ordinarily ſtartled and troubled at the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the event: which is no ſmall preſage that the Lord is going
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61235:34"/>along with the deſign; and ſhould be an encouragement to all intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Men to joyn in the work; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that which the enemies of the Truth fear moſt; all that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the truth in the love thereof, ſhould ſeek moſt to bring to paſſe. This work of a Correſpondency between <hi>England</hi> and Foraign Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, for the intereſt of the Goſpel, was one of the wiſe reſolutions and propoſalls, which the Parliament in the year 1641. in their Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance to the late King made, as to be one of the effects of their Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Reformation then intended: but the unfortunate Man followed a contrary courſe to the way propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and did not only decline the Reformation; but correſponding with the enemies of the Goſpel ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a doore unto them to bring in their Superſtition into <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to enlarge it in <hi>Ireland.</hi> But God hath diſappointed won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61235:35"/>all thoſe deſignes, as hath been evident to all the world: therefore having begun with them, when they were at the height of their undertaking to overthrow it, we may aſſuredly conclude that he will alſo make a full end. For he hath declared his purpoſe that he will <hi>ariſe for his people to ſhake terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the earth;</hi> and what he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, who ſhall diſannull it? And when his hand is ſtreched out to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute his purpoſe, who ſhall turne it back? Therefore let all that are upright in heart be ſtrong to work with the Lord for the uniting of his Saints, that their light may break forth as the noone day; and the glory of the Lords goodneſſe may be ſeen upon them. Let none look back as <hi>Lots</hi> wife did to regret the loſſe of temporal conveniencies; but all look forward to follow the <hi>footſteps of the Almighty, who is gone forth of his place</hi> to ſhew himſelf on the head of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61235:35"/>his people united in his fear &amp; love, to lead them unto reſt; and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>England</hi> is to march in the Front before all the reſt whom the Lord employs in this his enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the hearty expreſſions of our wiſhes from abroad, towards you moſt Noble Senators, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Nation whom you repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: that as by the good hand of God upon the Spirit of your leaders you are become honorable among your Friends, and terrible to your Enemies; ſo you would ſtrengthen his hands in the workes, whereon the Lord hath ſet him, and with him joyne your Counſell and ſtrength to help the Lord againſt the mighty: Remembering that it is not alone by outward power, that deliverance will be wrought to the people of God, but by the Spirit of the Lord: By the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of love and unity amongſt your ſelves; of Righteouſnes and love
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61235:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>towards all that erre by ignorance, and <hi>are not made the accurſed thing:</hi> and of faithful confidence and hope towards God. If you entertain the Motions of this ſpirit, and deſpiſe not the ſuggeſtions which from a ſingle heart we have offered as the teſtimony of our affections for your welfare; We are ſure the <hi>Lord will be with and will go before you, and the God of Iſrael will be your rereward; &amp; he will make you as a poliſhed ſhaft in his quiver to peirce through the very heart of his enemies;</hi> and that it may ſo fall out, you ſhall have with the conſtant hearty prayers to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God for your proſperity, in due time alſo, the faithful hands of your humbly affectionate freinds abroad; who are known to the <hi>Lord whom you ſerve;</hi> and who know you in him by his ſervice.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61235:36"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
